A Guide to the Norfleet Family Papers, 1823-1874
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Norfleet Family Papers, 1823-1874
The Library of Virginia
21871
.15 cubic feet
Norfleet Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Fillmore Norfleet, 30 June 1941.
Biographical Information
Elisha Norfleet was born 15 November 1800 in Nansemond County, Virginia, to Christopher Norfleet (ca. 1761-1812) and Clotilda James (ca. 1770-184-), the 5th of 10 children and the 4th of 5 sons. Primarily a farmer, Norfleet amassed a large amount of real estate in the county. By the outbreak of the Civil War, Norfleet owned over 30 slaves. When the Union army occupied Suffolk and Nansemond County, Norfleet moved his family to Henderson, North Carolina, returning to Nansemond at the end of the war. He married Sarah Ann Lassiter (1804-1850) 30 December 1824 and they had 13 children. He then married Sarah Elizabeth Riddick (1833-1910) 20 November 1851 and they had 8 children, including John Ballentine Norfleet (1866-1955) who served as mayor of Suffolk from 1907 to 1911. Elisha Norfleet died 25 December 1869.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1823-1874, of the Norfleet family of Nansemond County, Virginia, consisting of deeds for land in Nansemond County and in Norfolk County and Suffolk, Virginia; deeds for mills, personal property, chattel, and interest in an estate; surveys and plats of land in Nansemond County; bonds to Elisha Norfleet (1800-1869) of Nansemond County; and will of Elisha Norfleet and account of Norfleet's estate by Jethro Riddick.
Contents List
- Deed, dated 26 March 1823 and recorded 27 March 1823, for 30 acres in Nansemond Countyfrom Mary Bates to James Bates, both of Nansemond County.
- Deed, dated April 1825 and recorded 3 November 1825, for 37 acres in Nansemond County from Henry P. and Margaret Gwinn to Elisha Norfleet (1800-1869), all of Nansemond County.
- Deed, dated and recorded 6 May 1826, for mill and land in Nansemond County from Elisha and Sarah Ann (1804-1850) Norfleet to Mills Riddick of Nansemond County.
- Survey, 10 January 1827, for 71 acres in Nansemond County made by Peter Roberts.
- Deed, dated 21 June 1828 and recorded 11 August 1828, for certain personal property between Henry P. Gwinn, Elisha Norfleet, and James L. Cherry, all of Nansemond County.
- Deed, dated 23 February 1828 and recorded 11 August 1828, for 50 acres in Nansemond County from Henry P. and Margaret Gwinn to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated and recorded 24 June 1829, for 12 acres in Nansemond County from Allen and Susan Jones of Norfolk County, Virginia, to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 31 July 1829 and recorded 4 August 1829, for 30 or 40 acres in Nansemond County from John T. Kilby of Nansemond County to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 28 September 1829 and recorded 30 September 1829, for 65 acres in Nansemond County, involving Henry P. Gwinn, party of the first part, John S. Denson of Nansemond County, party of the second part, and Mills Riddick, party of the third part.
- Deed, dated and recorded 2 January 1834, for 2 acres in Nansemond County from Sally Bridger to Elisha Norfleet.
- Survey, 19 January 1834, for 161 acres in Nansemond County belonging to Elisha Norfleet and John Parker of Nansemond County made by Norfleet Jones.
- Deed, dated and recorded 3 November 1835, for 75 acres in Nansemond County from Frances Meredith of Nansemond County to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 21 March 1836 and recorded 1 April 1836, for 1 acre in Nansemond County from Mills Riddick to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 16 March 1836 and recorded 11 April 1836, for 59 1/4 acres in Nansemond County from Benjamin and Eliza Riddick of Nansemond County to Elisha Norfleet.
- Plat, 23 May [1837?], for 1 acre in Nansemond County belonging to Elisha Norfleet made by Nathaniel P. Phillips.
- Deed, dated and recorded 30 November 1837, for 6 acres in Nansemond County from John B. and Custine Benton of Nansemond County to Elisha Norfleet.
- Bond, 27 June 1838, from George W., John R., and John H. Purdie to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 27 June 1838 and recorded 20 July 1838, for 60 acres in Nansemond County from George W. and Evelina Purdie to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 26 February 1839 and recorded 12 March 1839, for 1 acre in Nansemond County from John and Mary Parker of Nansemond County to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 27 May 1839 and recorded 8 July 1839, for 34 acres in Nansemond County from John B. and Custine Benton to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 19 November 1839 and recorded 26 November 1839, for land in Nansemond County from Richard H. and Marianna Riddick to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 12 February 1841 and recorded 18 February 1841, for a lot in the town of Suffolk, Virginia, from Thomas B. Virnelson and James L. and Martha Gwaltney to Content Judkins, all of Nansemond County.
- Deed, dated and recorded 4 December 1841, for all rights in certain land from William J. Nottingham of Nansemond County to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated and recorded 26 September 1842, for all rights in the estate of Thomas Johnson involving James L. Jones, party of the first part; Elisha Norfleet and James P. Gwinn, party of the second part; and Robert Riddick, Jr., party of the third part.
- Deed, dated 19 November 1842 and recorded 24 November 1842, for land in Nansemond County from Mills and Mary Riddick to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 18 March 1843 and recorded 8 April 1843, for 90 acres in Nansemond County from Frederick Hall to John R. Kilby, both of Nansemond County.
- Deed, dated 25 July 1843 and recorded 29 July 1843, for 7 acres in Nansemond County from William H. Pedin of Nansemond County to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 26 February 1844 and recorded 10 June 1844, for 80 acres in Nansemond County involving John Baker, party of the first part, James E. Smith, party of the second part, and Robert R. Smith, party of the third part, all of Nansemond County.
- Deed, dated 1 July 1845 and recorded 3 July 1845, for certain land in Norfolk County from John Chandler and William H. Wilson, trustees, to Hardy Norfleet (1808-1891), all of Norfolk County.
- Deed, dated and recorded 3 December 1845, for certain land in Norfolk County from George M. Bain of Portsmouth, Virginia, to Hardy Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 28 April 1846 and recorded 9 November 1846, for 90 acres in Nansemond County from John R. and Martha Kilby and Thomas J. and Ann Kilby to Alexander C. Dickinson, all of Nansemond County.
- Deed, dated 30 November 1846 and recorded 5 December 1846, for certain personal and chattel estate involving Richard Lawrence, party of the first part, John R. Kilby, party of the second part, and Thomas J. Kilby, party of the third part.
- Deed, dated and recorded 8 February 1847, for 350 acres in Nansemond County from Josiah and Irena Murphrey to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 15 June 1847 and recorded 1 July 1847, for 100 acres in Nansemond County from Charles and Ellen Walters to Alexander C. Dickinson.
- Deed, dated and recorded 28 July 1847, for certain personal property involving Washington Read, party of the first part, James B. Wills, party of the second part, and Charles F. Hoffman, party of the third part.
- Deed, dated 1 November 1846 and recorded 28 July 1849, for 60 acres in Nansemond County from Francis D. and Emily Holladay to Alexander C. Dickinson.
- Deed, dated 29 April 1850 and recorded 18 June 1850, for certain land in Nansemond County from James Murdaugh of Norfolk County to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 25 June 1850 and recorded 3 July 1850, for certain land in Nansemond County from Isaac Diggs to Stephen P. Johnson, both of Nansemond County.
- Deed, dated and recorded 26 November 1850, for 82 acres in Nansemond County from Hardy and Martha Norfleet to Elisha Norfleet.
- Deed, dated 31 December 1857 and recorded 7 January 1858, for certain personal property from George W. Singleton, trustee, to William D. Wood, trustee.
- Will, dated 4 December 1869 and recorded 10 January 1870, of Elisha Norfleet.
- Account, 12 May 1874, by Jethro Riddick (1803-1874) of Nansemond County of the estate of Elisha Norfleet from January 1872 to January 1874.
- Plat, no date, for 20 acres belonging to Thomas P. Smith of Nansemond County made by James Blakeney.
- Plat, no date, for 21 acres belonging to William Adkins of Nansemond county made by James Blakeney.